This normally wouldn't be an
hour, but we're going to chop it
down and speed it up and keep
the back half hour for q&a as we
go. Great. So we're gonna talk
about hiring a head of product.
And as Mark said, I think this
is really a general topic. But
because I'm a pure software
product management guy, I'm
telling it from my side of the
story. So, you know, we'll be
able to generalize quite a bit,
but we'll take it from that
point of view.
Okay, just a very brief
introduction for me. Quick hint,
I'm on the right in this photo.
On the left is my other office
manager, Celeste, Olivia may
join us as you saw during the
warm up. So what's important
about this for the talk is to
set up why I think I might have
something to say about it. I'm a
30 plus year veteran of Silicon
Valley b2b enterprise software.
So I had my first product
management job in the late 80s.
It's not a new thing. And these
days, I'm spending a lot of my
time helping software companies
design their product
organizations, coaching their
product leaders. And then you
know, the statistic that's
probably important here. So in
the last 19 years, since I went
solo, I've done about 150
engagements with different
clients, of which a dozen are
what we've called the
smokejumper, VP product jobs. So
that's where I come into a
company as the interim or
temporary head of product for
usually a couple of quarters and
get everything straightened out.
I've also done a little over a
dozen assistance roles where I
help my clients figure out who
they need as head of product,
and then interview the
candidates and be part of the
the assessment team, which is
really where this is coming out.
So having done a few dozen of
these, I may be, you know, more
frequently in this role than
anyone else on the planet other
than folks who are in the search
business themselves.
So I've tried to pull together
some observations that might be
useful for us, you know, of
course in the narrow: how do we
hire head of product? And in the
broader: How do we apply lessons
to some of the other
departments?
Okay, let's jump in. The first
challenge I think we have is,
nobody seems to know what to
call this job. So here's our
caped crusader hero, we don't
know this dog's name. But what I
observe is that I'm going to use
the phrase head of product, H O,
P, because we need to call it
something. And I'm going to
specifically say that what we're
talking about is folks who
manage product managers. Again,
this would seem obvious, most of
this is obvious, but I'm
discovering that it's not.
Sometimes we call those folks
Chief Product Officer, VP,
Product Director, product,
group, product, lead, whatever,
whatever. And this person might
also have, I don't know, a
couple of designers, there might
be a market research person or
whatever. But I'm specifically
going to not talk about folks
who are mostly running
development or engineering
teams. So there's lots of the
piece of product out there with
many different names CIO, CTO,
General Manager, I observed that
if you are managing, let's say,
85 developers, and for product
managers, most of your brain is
on the development side of the
house, not the product side of
the house. So I'm going to not
include those folks in our
little breakdown here.
Okay, here's our little bad dog.
And, and a few of the failures
that I see over and over again,
as we say, you know, what are
the primary failures that either
I'm called in to fix, or I'm
stuck on the side of the road
watching the accidents for, and
The first one, which is maybe
where we're gonna spend most of
there's really three.
our time for the next 40
minutes, is companies that hire
somebody to be the head of
product, who's neither led a
product team, nor been a product
manager, this is a head
scratcher for me, but we'll
break it down a little bit.
The second failure mode I see
is, if you're the first product
person in the door at a startup,
or the first head of product at
a startup, it's pretty rare for
the founders to actually give up
the autonomy and control that
they need for you to succeed,
even though they say they do.
And so I see the duration of
that first head of product being
pretty short. The acronym
sometimes we use his MTBE,
meantime between executives.
And then the third thing that
really contributes I think to
what we're going to see is that
many of the folks at software
companies who lead software
companies who found companies
don't actually understand what
product management does. And so
they've got some real
misapprehensions or confusion
around what it is that they need
and have a product.
Okay, so because I don't want to
be talking the whole time, we're
going to do a little experiment
here. We're going to try a bit
of a tweetstorm. So if I can ask
get everybody to open up their
chat box. And here's the
question I want you to ask,
don't hit return yet. So type in
your answer, and then we'll all
hit it at once. So we can all
see it at once. If you are going
to be interviewing somebody as
your new potential VP of sales
or Chief Revenue Officer, what's
the first question or two, you
would want to ask them? I'll
give everybody a minute. And
then count to three, count to
four, count to five. All right,
when you have an answer, hit
Return, and I'll pick a few of
them out of here. Okay, that's
right.
Tell me about your first sales
job. How do you increase sales?
What's your sales strategy?
What's your sales process?
Excellent. How much revenue did
you earn last year? What was
your quota?
So those are all questions that
would suggest that we'd really
like to have somebody as our VP
of sales or chief revenue
officer who has been a
salesperson and maybe lead
salespeople. Because it turns
out there's a lot of art and
science. Yes, I do know Paul
Kenny, and I think he's
brilliant. And I rarely see a
company that hires a head of
sales who has not been in sales
before, although, in full
disclosure, one of my clients
had somebody running sales who's
really a finance guy from m&a.
And that's a lot more
challenging. Likewise, if we're
going to hire somebody, as our
Chief Financial Officer, we'd
really like to know that they
understand payroll, and how to
run an accounts payable or
receivables group, how to keep
our executives out of jail by
not running out of money. If
we're gonna hire somebody who's
a VP of engineering or a CTO, we
might, for instance, want them
to have built software before
that would be really handy.
Maybe even run a software team
or two, because if we dropped
somebody in his VP of
engineering, who thinks that
software is neat, and might like
to build some, someday, we've
got a lot of hurt on our hands.
Again, it would seem obvious,
but what I noticed over and over
again, and it's Tuesday, I had
this discussion twice yesterday
with some of my clients were at
the very, very top in the very
first position of the
requirements for this job of
head of product, what we don't
find is, in a product manager,
run a product team. Okay, so
let's, let's get back to our
animals just a little bit and
consider some different animals
we might want for this job.
All right. Certainly here,
here's my ideal candidate for
the head of product, you'll
notice this Australian Shepherd
is going to move the sheep
along. Everything about this
head of product job,
particularly at a startup that's
trying to find its way is
thinking about the market and
the segments, not the
individual, not the one sheep,
we've got to move the whole herd
to wherever the water is,
instead of letting them wander
in all directions. Do we have a
clear strategy? Is it tied to
what our development team is
going to do? We're going to
measure outcomes, can we move
the whole company along toward
our product goal and our revenue
goal. An important useful fact
here is that nobody works for
product management, we've got
lots of responsibility and
absolutely no authority. So
other than nipping at our heels
and moving people along, you
know, not many sticks to
swinging there. And a lot of it
is about long term thinking, if
we're going to get the whole
company toward a strategic
outcome, we're all going to have
to work together, we're going to
reduce distractions, we're going
to block interrupts, we're going
to hate one off requests from
customers that somehow are going
to distract us.
And I know as, as the many time
had a product, every single
department in the company is
going to wander at some point.
And we're going to have to keep
calling them back with
reminders. Who are we selling
to? Why are they going to buy?
Is this the most wonderful
thing? How do we talk about it?
Okay, so there's our animal
choice for head of product.
Let's pick a few more. Here's
our Chief Revenue Officer, our
VP of sales, very aggressive by
nature, you know, fast, lethal.
But what else do we know about
these, these hunting cats,
they're very focused, they bring
in the red meat, they tend to be
single account focused, right?
They're gonna find the weakest
prey out there, whichever the
envelope is easier to bring
down. And they're tremendously
focused on the current quarter.
Every salesperson I know can
tell me to the exact number, how
many days are left in the
quarter and how much of their
quota they've retired. And they
strongly believe that they
really know exactly what the
customer wants, even though
everything about selling is
about pushing our point of view
and getting the users or the
buyers or their prospects to say
yes, instead of delving deeply
and finding out what their real
issues are, so we can solve
them.
When I see product management
teams working for sales - so
either we move the product team
under the sales organization, or
we bring a head of sales over to
run product very quickly. What
we discover is the whole product
team has really become the order
ticking handmaidens to sales.
We're working on single decks
for single meetings or
customers. And we've given up
our whole strategic roadmap in
favor of whatever the top few
customers have asked for in the
last, I don't know, 10 minutes.
Okay.
So while I love having a head of
sales, a chief revenue officer,
and I've failed at doing it
myself, so I know it's really
hard, I can't see bringing those
folks in to run a product team.
Okay, some other choices. For
any of you who are CEOs, I hope
this looks familiar. When I see
a CEO who's doing well seven
other things, and has one of the
eight tentacles on the product
side, we've got a part time time
sliced person running product.
Generally, the failures I see
are around sampling. Many of you
who been CEOs know that the most
frequent calls you get are for
some big current customer who's
unhappy, because you never hear
from the small ones. And from
all of your sales teams to help
you lobby the next sales deal.
So you've got a very strange
recency bias view of life. And
you're not going to be able to
spend the time to worry about
strategy and product and pricing
and positioning and all the
things that product needs to do.
So we need one of these CEOs,
but we sure don't need them as a
head of product.
Okay, a few more choices. Let's
think about our VP engineering
because often, I see the product
team tucked in under the CTO,
the CIO, the VP engineering, and
these tend to be a lot more
methodical, they're orderly,
they're thoughtful, they're
patient, tough, right? Many of
them are nocturnal. We don't see
them so much early in the
office. And while they're very
communicative, they're mostly
communicate over Slack. So we
don't hear from them that much.
We know they're emotional, but
we don't see it so much. And
what I see often with VPs of
engineering, is they have this
very odd strange belief that all
of our customers are rational,
that they evaluate all the tech
or product strictly on a
rational straightforward bases.
And that buying and selling are
easy that what sales reps do is
they bring a price list and a
presentation, and they collect
purchase orders. So while it's
great, again, to have a VP of
engineering, they those folks
tend not to have strong
understanding of selling, or
marketing or positioning, or
many of the things that we have
to do on the product side. So
stuff gets sold. So not as bad
as some of the other choices.
But again, not my favorite,
let's go we have a couple more
choices.
Here's some folks I love at
every company I've ever worked
for. They're the customer
support and Customer Success
people. What do we know about
them? We know they're
tremendously huge supporters of
their customers, they're going
to go the extra, not just the
single kilometer, they'll
they'll go the extra 100 miles,
they do tend to be single
customer or single account folks
at a time. Often your customer
success team is assigned long
term to just one customer. And
as you can see here, they're
willing to take that one
customer over every bump and
through every traffic signal and
stopping at every corner,
whether that's good for the
company or not as a whole. So
they're never trained to say no,
they're trained to say yes, and
to help that one customer figure
out how to do the one special
thing. When we put our product
hats on, we usually take a
different point of view. Instead
of asking how we can help be of
the most help to our next
customer. We ask how we can
engineer away most of the human
support, can we make onboarding
easier? Can we create tools? Can
we make the workflows better?
How do we get out from under the
support and success work as
opposed to do more of it? And
know that we're the most
important folks on the planet?
Okay, take a breath here. I
think we've got maybe one more.
Here's the one that doesn't
happen so often, but I run into
sometimes we'll take a moment
because you all know what the
picture is going to be right? So
here's my new baby puppy, six
weeks, or maybe six months as a
product manager, excuse me, I
usually expect it's going to
take maybe three or four years
to grow this puppy up to be a
really, really terrific product
manager and another three or
four years to grow them up to be
a product leader where there
might be a director and heading
up a team.
And most importantly, having
done this a bunch of times I
know that when I', hiring
somebody who's never been a
product manager before I as the
product leader, I'm going to
spend a lot of time house
training, right coaching and
mentoring and business life
skills. We're not going to send
this puppy in to an important
meeting with our biggest
customer until we've given it
some training. And as every head
of product knows, there's going
to be a bunch of accidents and
we may have to clean up the
carpet. Add or even replace it a
few times. So, while I love
having newly minted or freshly
arrived product managers on the
team, I wouldn't put them in as
head of product.
Okay, so we're through most of
our animals. Let's, let's open
this up. Where are we? Here we
go. And I think we want to, we
want to ask you guys again,
let's come back to our
tweetstorm. Just for fun,
because I'm going to give us
briefly really three different
thoughts for, you know,
misconceptions that may be
underlying this. And I'm having
a lot of trouble finding my chat
window, but I'm sure we'll get
there. So go ahead. If anybody
has an idea, why don't you give
me an idea - one or two or three
- type them in, something that's
a core misconception from the
rest of the executive team,
about what product leadership is
or what we need? So I can break
those down. And don't wait, just
drop them in. It's just about
prioritizing work.
John, you're exactly right.
Doesn't know the real value.
Ouch, that hurts. It's all about
which feature next product owns
the voice of the customer?
Right? Getting software built
faster? That was the winning
answer I wanted. Only product
management knows the answers. I
believe that but nobody else
believes it, right? Why do we
need you anyway, engineering
builds it, I'd love it. These
are all spot on?
Okay, so here's the three I
picked out. The first one, and I
think several of you said there,
right? That what we really need
is we need product engineering
to say yes to the sales side of
the house more often. And so
therefore what product
management product leadership
should be doing? Is whipping the
engineers harder, right? How do
we get more stuff out of the
development side of the house.
The second thing I run into a
lot is, oh, well, our products
really very complicated. And so
nobody can understand our
product unless they have at
least one or two advanced
degrees in our thing. So it's
not possible to hire any product
managers, unless they also
happen to have been at a famous
university with a thesis on our
stuff, right.
And then the third one, which I
think several of you had there
is the executive team has this
odd belief that our strategies
are so clear, and so aligned and
the OKRs is so well written,
that everybody's going to just
do the right thing and be on the
right page without much help.
And honestly, I think I've never
found this to be true.
So let's unpack these three,
just a little bit. And here we
go. So if anybody's at this
engineering organization, but
this is every engineering team
or development team I've ever
met, there is no development
team on the planet that isn't
already overloaded and has too
much to do 2x 5x 10x. Yet, the
executive team tells us that
what we really want is to push
harder, right? So the executive
team, the go to market team,
there's usually some hot issue
in their head, right? Just got
off a call with a customer. But
every dev team is
oversubscribed. And so we end up
in this ADHD model of
roadmapping. Where every 2.5
minutes, it turns out, we've got
a new strategy. And the failure
mode I see. In fact, I'm writing
a really long piece for one of
my clients on this is that we
have too many number one items.
And our answer when something's
important is to make another new
thing. Another top number one
items, so we constantly add, and
the team actually never finishes
anything. Right? So the
reputation that engineering gets
is that they're losers or
slackers are sitting around
eating bonbons, when the root
issue of course, is we've taken
on four times as much as we can,
and we're thrashing.
Right second of these, right,
only our special experts can
understand here's our product
manager unable to find her way
through the maze, because too
complicated. And I've taken
notes over the years. And the
winner I think was, Oh, our
company's doing six factor
authentication. And no one can
understand Understand six factor
authentication, unless they've
got at least one or two advanced
degrees in CES and
authentication. So there is no
product manager who's going to
understand this. Now, that's a
bit of a problem, not just for
the product manager, but
probably for the customers,
right? Because if we can't
explain it to a product manager,
then we probably can't sell it
to anybody. Right? And when we
hire a subject expert who's
never worn the product badge
before, here's what I see.
First of all, those subject
experts usually don't ever think
about the newbies, the
onboarding, the economics,
they're always thinking about
the two or three buddies of
theirs, who are the power high
end users, and they routinely
decide that their point of view
is so much more accurate than
what anything we're going to
learn from customers is of
course customers don't know what
they want that They put
themselves in the place of
already knowing all the answers
instead of going out and doing
what every good product person
does, which is endlessly,
repeatedly every single day,
talking to lots of users and
customers and prospects and
partners and lost deals, to find
out what's actually true in the
world. And my observation is, if
you give your newly arrived
Product Manager a couple of
months of halftime, send them
out on the road, have them do 20
or 30 customer meetings, they'll
come back understanding
everything they need. So this
idea is I think, fallacious,
it's just not true. But so many
places end up hiring a subject
expert who honestly couldn't
spell product, if you gave him
all the consonants in the
correct order.
And then my third one here,
here's our geese all lined up.
Here's our beautiful strategy.
everything's aligned, everybody
knows where we're going. The
first thing I find when
customers or companies adopt
OKRs, is they adopt first just
some revenue OKRs. Right, our
goal for the quarter is to make
20 million. And, you know, that
might suggest that I'm going to
sell off some my household
furniture for revenue or stand
on the corner in a very short
skirt, it's not a pretty sight.
When we try to, to figure out
how to apply that to product,
it's a zero help in figuring out
what's more important, or most
important, because we haven't
yet gotten down to target
audiences and positioning and
where we're going to win where
we're going to not win.
The other thing I see in these
organizations is that all the
OKRs are really functional level
ones. Finance has its goals.
Marketing has its goals, and
they simply don't ever touch.
Part of what we do is head of
product back to our sheepdog is,
I spent an awful lot of my time
trying to get my executive peers
to line up their their goals and
maybe measure the right thing. I
don't know if you've ever been
in a company where the support
team has a goal of shortening
their average call. And you know
what they do it. And the way
they do it is they throw folks
off the phone, and they don't
solve the problems. So those
people can call back, but the
average call is shorter. You
know, when we create goals, we
have to be really thoughtful,
because folks are going to do
just what we asked them paid
them to do.
Alright, so there's our three
misconceptions. Here's a sort of
takeaway thought for me, by the
way, I put a post up over the
weekend. That's the long form
text version of this. So anybody
who feels like they want to read
the 2000 words, just go to my
website, but he was the takeaway
from that, right? What are the
key skills, right? A lot of
negotiating a lot of empathy, a
lot of horse trading among the
internal stakeholders. But
somebody's got to stand up for
the real customers. I'm always
channeling the original Tron
movie from 1982, where they say,
we fight for the users, we don't
fight for the stakeholders, we
fight for the users.
Okay, so having done all that,
I'm going to flash past three
quick slides here. I'm not even
going to bother reading them
all. But I put together some
interview questions that when we
look at the videotape, or you
pull down the slide set, you
might want to borrow the next
time you're interviewing you had
a product. So instead of asking
how can we get more on the
roadmap? Here's a couple of
better questions, right? And
instead of how are you going to
get more productivity out of our
development team, whipping them
harder? Here's an alternative.
Right? Likewise, instead of
asking, Are you a subject
expert? Have you worked in our
exact tech segment and already
know what customers want? Wrong?
Here's a couple of ways you
might unpack that in an
interview.
And then one last one. I'm not a
fan of Net Promoter Score,
because it's pretty random and
doesn't give us much information
and it's easy to manipulate. So
here's a few better questions,
then NPS score to figure out how
we're going to understand what
our customers are doing. Okay, I
want to leave a lot of time for
questions. So let's go to a few
takeaways. Right? Got to have a
treat at the end. Everybody got
to the end. Here's your treat.
So here's our three things,
right. And if we were in the
hall together in Boston, I might
actually ask everybody to stand
up and repeat this. But I think
you can do that in the privacy
of your own desks here. Right?
Product management experience,
product leadership experience.
Before subject market technical
specifics, right? Please, Oh,
please, oh, please, don't bring
in somebody just because they
know your tech.
The thing we do, how do we add
value? Why do we care? Why does
anybody else care? It's because
often the product management
team and therefore the product
management leader, are the
people balancing long term
scratch strategy against current
quarter execution. And we are
endlessly battling the fight of
should we do this one special
little thing for this one big
customer who promises never to
ask us anything else again, at
least until later in the day? Or
are we going to let the entire
development team be diverted to
whatever three or four shiny
objects have come up in today's
sales calls? And then, you know,
what do we do leadership skills,
things we need, right? We need
to be able to keep the rest of
the executive team focused. not
trivial.
We need to keep our eyes on the
market success, the segments,
the larger picture, not single
accounts, we got to spend a
tremendous amount of time
understanding and loving all of
our peers across all the
organizations. And then last of
all, back to our puppy photo.
We've got to raise those young
uns, those soon to be product
managers, mentoring, tutoring,
teaching them how to do it,
cleaning up the carpet as
necessary. So that's the things
I think we're looking for in a
head of product. And I hope that
that helps us helps you with a
better frame around that. And
then just circling back to
Mark's point from the very
beginning, you could apply this
to any of your functions. I just
happen to tell it as a product
leadership story, because that's
my part of the problem. All
right, here's how to find me.
That's the website. That's the
email. That's the Twitter
handle. Anybody notice it's hard
to spell, but it's all the same?
Let's have a little round of
applause first.
I'll pick a few of these off the
chat, just start. Anybody wants
to break in with with the audio
later. So so lots of good
questions.
I'm going to start with with the
top one from from Brian: these
issues have existed since the
beginning of software product
businesses. Why is it so hard to
solve? I think part of it is
that most of what product
management does is sort of
transparent, right? When it's
working, you don't see it. And
when it's broken, you're usually
miss attributing it. So most of
the calls I get are from CEOs
who tell me their engineering
team doesn't work hard enough or
isn't productive or is lazy. And
then when we open the box, we
figure out that there's no goals
for the company, or they're in
complete conflict. And the CEO
comes down no more frequently
than let's say, every 25 minutes
to the development organization
with a new number one priority.
And they're dejected and
frustrated. And what they really
need more than anything else is
a product management team,
especially a head of product,
that's the semi permeable
membrane, the funnel, the
umbrella, such that the rest of
the company has to go through
something painful, before we can
interrupt what we've already
agreed to be in the sprint.
So that's not the obvious skill.
Everybody thinks about writing
user stories. Honestly, I don't
care about user stories, and I
don't care what format we have
them in. Turns out a
grammatically correct user story
is usually probably still the
wrong thing we should build.
It's not the grammar we want to
check. It's whether we did our
homework and truly understand
our customers, which is hard to
see. So the other thing, the
failure mode here is a lot of
folks have never been at a
company where product management
was any darn good. And so they
don't have a model in their head
what we're supposed to do.
Okay, good. Tim Burgess: How do
you build consensus or strength
of your voice when the other
executives are ostensibly more
important? or higher profile?
Really good question. I think of
every good product manager, as a
student of human behavior,
right? We've all read Dale
Carnegie's book from the 1920s,
about how to make friends and
influence people, we all
understand what the different
departments value and how
they're measured. We think a lot
about motivations and goals and
alignment. And so for instance,
the way I talk, the marketing
and sales side of the house,
through my roadmap, is entirely
different than the way I'd go
through it with my engineering
team. It's the same roadmap. But
on the sales side, we're almost
all talking about who it's for,
why they want it, and how can we
should be able to get full price
for it. Whereas on the
engineering side, we're talking
a lot more about the inner
workings of the problems we're
solving. So there's a lot of
channeling the different
audiences and what they need.
And then there's a tremendous
amount of honestly, horse
trading and alignment here.
Many of you know this, but every
single person in your support
organization expects to get 100%
of developments effort against
fixing bugs. And everybody in
your sales organization expects
engineering to spend 100% of
their effort on whatever these
new deals need. And your success
team wants 100% of their effort
against simpler workflows and
better onboarding. And your
engineering team wants to spend
80% on fixing your tech debt and
doing factoring. So there's
actually no way to get to a good
answer here. Unless we set up
some you know allocations in
agreements about how we're going
to work here. So I spend a lot
of my time trying to get
consensus on how we're going to
spend our general money before
we fall down the rabbit hole of
tickets. Okay.
David Carta: what order would
you hire people beyond founders,
CFO, product manager, VP sales.
That's a hard one. Because
usually the founders come from
some side, if they're
technologists, I probably want
to get maybe an early business
development person as opposed to
a salesperson. Because for the
first year, honestly, we don't
know what we're selling. And
we're going to have to take our
word back a few times, I usually
expect a company a startup to
hire its first full time product
manager, and about 12 people.
Because then by then you've got
a development team and
engineering team of six or
seven, that's enough to justify
a product manager, I don't
really see a head of product or
VP of product until we get to, I
don't know 3035. Because there's
just not enough scope there. If
I come in as the head of product
at a 12 person company, I have
to be also willing to do all the
individual contributor work,
which is fine, but not everybody
is willing to do that. Okay.
That's a great question from Go
ahead. And Mark Davis wants to
ask the CEO to validate they do
in fact, want to give up the
reins.
This is hard, because almost
every CEO will say yes to that.
Really no, right?
That's right, in practice, so
I'm not sure there's a question
I asked the CEO directly. Advice
I give to folks in every job: if
you're interviewing for a job at
a company is find some folks who
work at the company who are not
on the interview roster, get
into LinkedIn figured out who
you know, or who you're
connected, one hop away from. In
a better time, I would have said
take them out to breakfast. But
right now, it's virtual coffee,
and ask a lot of questions about
the company. Because first of
all, you want to learn about the
company before you get too far
in the interview cycle.
But a question I always ask or
some variation is, would you
recommend a good friend of yours
work at this company? Surprising
how often that answer is no. How
about did the CEO have a bad
childhood? Often? That's it.
Yes. Right? Well, what we're
looking we're looking for here
is somebody who's not
sufficiently biased by being in
the interview cycle, which means
they're trying to sell me on the
job and figure out if I'm
selling hard enough, but find
somebody whose objective is
going to tell you what's going
on, what are the company
problems? How are they doing?
Are there layoffs coming? Just
does this person get joy coming
into the office? Because I find
when you could answer get good
answers to that your CEO is most
likely doing a lot of the right
things. And there's a good
chance that that head of product
is going to be allowed to
succeed. I would say half the
time on those discussions. What
I hear back from people is, huh,
huh? Can we take that one
offline? And no, I wouldn't
recommend that my best friend
take a job here. Right? You
don't want to work there. Move
on. There's other jobs. Okay,
how about one other one? Should
I just pick one out? Or if
there's somebody who wants to
come in on audio? That would be
fun?
I think yeah, let's find someone
that wants to come in on audio.
So I find that in a lot of
companies, the head of product
means a lot of things. And
sometimes it's like, encroaching
across everything in the
company. And it's like owning
the customer. And I don't know
why. But so I just want to
clarify and have some opinion
from you. Like, what are the
what should be the
accountabilities of the head of
product or the accountabilities
of the product function?
Yeah, and this is hard, because
none of the things that Product
Management delivers are direct
customer consumables, right? And
products not actually in control
of any almost any of the
resources in the company. It's
hard to pin either success or
failure directly on product. So
I look for a lot of of secondary
things. Does everybody in the
company really understand what's
on the roadmap? Are we selling
to the right segments? Are we
mostly able to prop up our
prices and sell for something
near list price? A good
secondary thing is that sales
doesn't hate engineering. And
engineering doesn't hate sales.
Because by the way, if that's
the case, product either can't
succeed, or has failed
miserably, right. So notice,
those are all sort of
interstitial things. Do we have
a product strategy that we stick
to? Again, you can knock that
down from almost any department,
but if product succeeding those
are things that everybody
immediately says yes to. And so
the head of product is as much
intent internal salesperson for
clarity and strategy and
segmentation in targeting and
staying on focus as anything
else. Thanks. Sure.
So Peldi asked a question, which
was skelding. Any tips for
founders, CEOs to delegate Head
of Product responsibilities?
Probably being unusually shy
today?
Yeah. I don't know why Peldi.
But I think the that is the
right question, which is, can I
feel comfortable enough
delegating to the head of
product. And generally, the
failure mode here is around the
CEO believing that they are in
fact sampling the customer base
adequately, and that I know what
customers want, because I'm
talking to a lot of customers.
And the reason that doesn't hold
up is because at least at this
stage, almost all the
conversations that the CEO is
having with customers are
pushed, they're selling, they're
trying to get somebody to agree.
And what you do when you listen
to those calls with the CEO is
you find out the CEO is talking
70% or 80% of the time, which is
a sales call. And the folks at
the other end are either
politely listening or raising
small objections. But they're
not really saying what they
think the other thing that CEOs
and founders get is they get the
rapid escalations from the few
large customers of random things
they're unhappy about. And so
they decide that all customers
are having this problem, because
they're sampling badly, right.
And so, as a head of product,
what I need is some agreement
from the CEO, that if I can show
data, if my team is interviewing
40 customers a month or 90
customers a month, that we're
going to get believed that when
we identify that 65% of the
customers have an issue, but
it's not the one that CEO heard
about this morning, that we're
gonna get a hearing on that and
facts matter. And that's really
hard emotionally for the CEO,
because, you know, we're all the
center of our universes. And we
believe that what we're seeing
is a you know, an effective and
well sampled pattern.
Okay, I'm gonna pick one more,
Tim, we got from Tim, how about
Elizabeth Aveda: when should a
company hire it's first product
manager? I think we touched
that, you know, again, I'm
thinking like 12 employees, 14
employees.
Let's see what we got. Igor
says: In what form is
understanding the customer
captured? Is it just in a
product managers head, this is a
really hard problem, because
it's rather unstructured. One of
the ways I coach my heads of
product and product managers is,
first of all, every time we
interview a customer, assuming
it's not a sales call, I want to
include on the call a designer
and developer. Now, they
probably don't talk, I run the
interview. But it's very clear,
they hear different things than
I do, and they listen for
different things.
And we usually have some regime
where either they write me a
post it note, or they drop me a
Slack message on the side for
questions I'm missing, right, we
might have an hour's
conversation with a customer. So
we're going to capture that
we're gonna record it with
permission, of course, don't
want to break the law, we're
going to put that in a
repository. But right next to
it. At the very end of the call,
as soon as we're done before it
falls out of our heads, we're
going to among ourselves, pick
the three or four or five
takeaways, lessons, interesting
things, put them in bullets at
the very top, and send around to
the rest of the company, the
three bullets and a link to the
recording. That's important
because we do it right away. So
a recency bias isn't going to
get us in trouble. It helps
because the rest of the company
starts to notice that the
product team actually talks to
customers all the time.
And then, in general, I find
that we don't know the right
questions until 10 interviews in
or 15 interviews and we have to
go back and read our notes.
Because something popped up in
five of those conversations,
that was so bizarre, that we
never even thought to ask and
we're going to go back to our
notes back to our recordings,
and figure out if it was a
pattern. So that's a way that we
can share them out, get this
summary to the rest of the
world. And anybody who needs to
dig deep configure out which
transcript or recording is going
to have the detailed stuff in
it.
Hey, thanks for just a great
talk and answering so many
questions generously. I was
wondering if you could talk a
little bit more about the
smokejumper role and outside the
context of just fighting a
burning fire but also like as a
transition or even alternative
to hiring a full time w two
executive.
Yeah, so I've done about a dozen
of those. And every time I
promised myself not to do it
again. Because honestly, they're
they're really hard and
irrationally painful. And it
does borrow from the firefighter
terminology because the, the
smoke jumpers are the ones who
are parachuted on the far side
of the fire, to knock down all
the fuel, and they don't get to
go home, smelly and tired and
smoky until they fought their
way back through the fire. I
don't advise anyone to do this,
if they have a choice. You're
bringing in an outsider who
doesn't know the company and
doesn't know the product, I'm
generally much more effective in
that first quarter, or quarter
and a half. And fixing
organizational issues, and
process issues and goal issues,
I'm never gonna be smart enough
about your product in three
months, to really have strong
opinions about the product
details.
So generally, I'm called in when
it's really broken. And I want
to leave as soon as possible.
And the company wants me to help
them hiring a replacement as
soon as possible. Because every
company deserves a full time
head of product, who has the
long term understands the trade
offs, loves the customers with
all their heart and soul, and
understands how to move the
other executive players around
the board. So we get the right
things built and shipped. And
that's a lot of internal
discovery. It's a lot of
relationship building.
The one dirty secret here, which
since we're recording
everybody's going to know is as
the interim, here's here's my
other office manager, by the
way, as the interim head of
product, I can say and do things
that no full time employee would
ever say or do. I can be as
blunt with the CEO and pull them
aside for coaching about things
that you would never do if you
want to keep your job, because
I'm leaving anyway. And there's
no stock options for me. And
there's no bonus for me. My job
is to clean it up and get the
heck out. And so I have a lot
more freedom of movement. But
for a limited time, because you
don't get away with that for
more than a quarter or two. And
I'm usually burned out by then
anyway, so time to go home. I
can't I can't tell you that
that's something you would love.
But it's strong medicine when
you need it.
Well, that was actually a reason
for picking on picking on Jeff.
He asked that question earlier
on about relative roles, or
roles of head of product versus
some of the other bits of the
team. Jeff, do you want to
speak?
The question that Tomas asked in
rich well answered to pretty
much covered the majority of
that, like from the standpoint
that? Yeah, I think there's this
really interesting thing where
this sort of there's these
accountabilities, probably the
the product team typically has
that there is responsibilities
are tough to fall through. And,
again, I thought rich painted it
really well. Maybe the only
thing I would add, there was the
other nuance was, yeah, if we
were just complete a more
organizational picture. And that
same sort of vein, what then is
the accountabilities of, say
engineering and maybe marketing
in this role of figuring out the
product. Conversely, to it Rich
said, because there's this
interesting trend, where some
people have talked about how
product management is a
separate, not as a role. It's
obviously a very important role
in the company to, to focus on
these accountabilities. But
that, as a separate vertical
department in a company is a
could be a little problematic.
In other words, why isn't
product considered part of the
engineering organization, for
example, an organization right.
And the challenge, if you have a
13 person company, you can't
have I mean, 13 departments, but
I observe that the engineering
team is really measured and
rewarded by getting things done.
But they're not measured and
rewarded for getting the right
things done. And it's not their
competency to make that call.
And on the marketing side, in a
good company, we've got a
product focus one. And so
marketing is really focusing on
the outbound positioning and
segmentation, and nurturing and
all the things that are that are
core to marketing. In general,
the marketing folks are a little
lightweight in terms of product
knowledge and internals. When we
have marketing folks spec out
products, we have really good
UX, but nothing under the hood,
soy, soy products sort of
halfway between. But in every
organization, we draw the line
in a different place. There's no
perfect, and it's so much about
how the different execs are
going to divide up the world
where they are the work in a way
that everybody can get along and
the fistfights in the alleys or
the the aisles of the office are
minimized. One last thought and
then I'll close.
We've got a few more questions.
Emily. Emily, could you just say
something.
I don't reload because people
get distracted but yeah, there
we go. That's my background
everybody. Self esteem boost for
the day.
For Emily, there's a couple of
questions and then quite a few
You're different people asking
about early stage companies,
Nick mer or Ben Ebong. Do you
want to pipe up and talk about
pm and roles and
responsibilities?
Yeah, hey, guys. Hey, rich, I
think you mentioned when you
should invest in a PLM,
essentially around a 12 person
team when you get to that stage,
but what happens if you're
trying to get to that stage? Who
should be tackling those roles
and responsibilities? And how do
you do that effectively? Maybe
you're a Product Manager and
CEO, maybe you're not.
It's a real challenge. Yeah. And
I'm not I'm seeing more true
startups two, and three and five
person startups where one of
those folks is, in fact, at
heart, a product manager. And I
think that gets us along the
discovery or validation track
really fast, I just don't see
most companies being able to
afford it. Right. So and that
person's even, even if they're
100% product originally, they're
probably doing three other jobs,
right? At a startup, we're all
doing a bunch of jobs.
So what I'd say is, I think it's
really, really important or
useful for a startup to have
somebody who's got product
management experience. But I'm
not sure at a four person
company that we're going to have
anybody whose sole job and name
tag says Product Management
because there's, there's not
enough division of labor in a
company that size.
I was just gonna pick something
up because Kevin Davis had a
good comment here, full
disclosure had been fired more
than once in this failure mode.
I've got to tell you, I've been
fired more than once in this
failure mode, too. So only, you
know, a handful of times, but it
was very instructive and good to
deflate my ego from where I
thought it was. Okay, I'm sorry,
Mark, you were going to take us
somewhere else?
Yeah, I was just gonna ask John
Saltz, if he wants to talk about
where product marketing should
fit.
Yes. You mentioned the marketing
sort of spectrum between
marketing and product
management. I'm wondering
product marketing. Yeah, big
enough where you need product
marketing, which we're big
enough, right? Yeah. It's more
of knowing the products and then
doing the marketing function.
What do you think about that?
I think, it's a hard call,
right. So when there's enough
product marketers, or enough
product marketing to have a
department, right, the two
choices one is to have it report
to marketing. And often the
product marketers feel a little
unloved and left out, because
they're doing something, you
know, somewhat more intellectual
is maybe a strong word, but it's
more content driven, it's more
subjective. It's very closely
tied to sales. And often the
product marketers feel unloved
by the demand gen side of the
house. But it's one of the two
choices. And at least, we know
that when we bring out a new
product, they'll be some
campaigns behind it, because
they're in the same
organization. And the messaging
will be good when we move it
under the head of product,
because sometimes I see product
marketing as part of the product
team next to product management.
What we've done is on the
positive side, we're getting a
lot better communications
between the product marketers
and the product managers were
much more likely to describe the
products correctly, to know who
they're for to have that stuff.
But often what we've lost is the
really tight connection to the
rest of marketing. So there's
this pendulum effect. Sometimes
I see where we have product
marketing on the marketing side
for 15 months, and then we
decide it would be better on the
product side for 15 months, and
then we think it would be better
on the marketing side for 15
months. And those folks get a
little whiplash. But, you know,
I think all product folks figure
out that we have to fill the gap
that the organization creates.
So no matter how we divide
people up, there are natural
gaps. And as the product folks,
we have to see those we have to
reach across we have to be
triply quadruple ly pushy about
communicating and loving the
folks across the gap because
everybody is across the aisle
from us. And, you know, we're
always papering over whatever
division we created. To non
answer, but it's my answer.
Right, Patrick Quinn, who
traditionally if he doesn't ask
a number of questions at any BoS
Conference. Isn't really at the
conference. Patrick, you've got
a question about experience
knowledge.
And and it looks like that's
about Scrum and Agile. So I'll
pick up Patrick's question. So I
think it's essential. I think
it's required that product
managers really understand how
their software is built. I think
there's no excuse for that. And
so we have to be agile
practitioners, right? We and but
in the broad sense, not in
honest again, I don't care if
you're Kanban or Scrum or
halfway in between your XP,
you're right. I've been at this
game so long that I know that
those are all right solutions
for some situations, I don't
think the product folks get to
be dogmatic about how the
software is built. It's not
their call. But we have to know
where we fit in. And probably
three places where it's really
important one is, we have to get
our problem statements or
whatever they are in the right
format. So our engineers and
developers are actually going to
engage with them. Notice, I
didn't say solutions, I said
problems, right.
The second is, I think we need
to be in every retrospective,
because so many of the issues
that come up on our development
teams are out of scope for the
developers themselves, right?
They can't fix organizational
problems, they can't fix lack of
focus on the sales side. They
can't fix weird, you know,
things that marketing's doing,
and and so my product managers
and I show up to the
retrospectives. So we take
assignments out of that to go
fix things, or lobby folks who
are outside the development team
that are blocking things for
development, right.
And then the third one is, we as
product folks are the semi
permeable shields were the
blockers to everybody who wants
to interrupt the current sprint,
I was just working with somebody
yesterday. And we defined the
conditions under which somebody
else in the company can break
the sprint, and it is the list
of one and it is p zero system
down. Customers can't use our
software, right? If our cloud is
offline, if our users can't log
in or enter data, we all stop
what we're doing, and we get it
fixed. But anything other than
that product managers have to
throw their bodies in the way of
all the other interrupts there's
nothing so important that we
can't wait a half a week until
the next sprint starts. And so
we have to live the Agile story,
we have to be part of the Agile
story. But I don't actually care
about the details that happen,
you know that the inside
baseball inside the sprint,
other than that the team's
working and I can help them. So
there's an outer loop, agile
here, as opposed to the inner
loop agile of single story
single points. Right? How do we
support agile as an
organization's organization?
Awesome. Thank you. Cool.
All right. Ben McDonald. So what
are your thoughts on pragmatic
marketing framework? But let's
extend that I mean, the almost
infinite number of frameworks.
Yeah. And for everything, I
guess, and I know, the pragmatic
folks are really smart, and
they're helping educate up the
product, folks, here's my
observation. There are, I don't
know, maybe no more than a dozen
or two different frameworks for
product management, they are all
morally the same. You know, you
need to have your own framework,
if you're going to put it on
your logo and promote it and
sell books and put people
through your class. But I've
never actually found anybody who
directly implements any of them
as written. So first of all,
they're just boxes on a page
with some templates. Going to a
class for two days does not
teach you how to be a product
manager.
My good friend Scott Sal Horst
out of Austin taught me that a
weekend at the dude ranch
doesn't make you a cowboy.
Right. And so it's true mark,
sorry. So I know that I want to
send my folks off maybe to a
class or two, because we're
gonna get a common vocabulary,
and we're gonna maybe have some
common templates, you know, get
on the same tools. But none of
that is the essence of product
management, the essence of
product management is embroiling
yourself in lots of customer
issues, and really, really,
really deeply understanding and
empathizing with what they need.
And then bringing that stuff
back to your development team,
where the much smarter folks are
going to help you figure out how
to solve it. And the workflows
are useful. But every time we
come to a new company, we blow
up those workflows and start
some new ones.
So I wouldn't confuse the grid
or the matrix or the flow
through diagram. With the
essential content. It's the same
problem as I don't know if you
guys know this, but writing a
book is just a matter of putting
100,000 words in a file. Now,
writing a good book is putting
the correct 100,000 words in the
file. And it's easy to get
confused between I showed up I
was in a meeting, I wrote a user
story and anything of value. So,
you know, let's just be cautious
about how much you can learn in
two days of a survey course,
rather than two years of living
with your mistakes by staying on
the same product long enough
that they all come back to bite
you.
Amazing. One last question. If
someone's got something rich,
you rattle through these so
quickly. Alright. I rattled.
Let's don't apologize.
Alright, so I have, I have one
last thought here, which, for
those of you who thought this
was going to be something you
wanted to emulate, right?
Whenever anybody comes up to me
and says they think they might
want to become a product
manager, or even worse, a
product leader, I think it's my
obligation spend the next 10 or
15 minutes, arguing the other
side. It's a, it's a
fascinating, wonderful, narrow
position. Most folks don't want
it most folks don't succeed at
it. It's not that much fun. I
observed that really smart folks
do product management for a few
years, and then something more
rewarding. And that's only
useful if I can tell you I
wasn't so smart because I've
been in product management for
30 plus years. So II OMEOJ
Whatever. Oh, nobody's old
enough. And anybody tell me what
the last punch card in the stack
says. And that's only useful
because each time I've been
fired, the three letters I write
on my whiteboard on my way out R
E. O. J. I put an away message
you said 404. Vice President not
found Nice. Okay. Great. Thanks
for everybody's attention. And
for Mark and the team for
letting me come play